So I understand that this meeting was planned,
علمت بأن هذا اللقاء قد رتب
and the slogan was From Was to Still.
تحت شعار "من كان إلى لا زال".
And I am illustrating Still.
وأنا أمثل "لا زال".
Which, of course, I am not agreeing with because,
لكنني بالطبع لا أوافق هذه الفكرة،
although I am 94, I am not still working.
لأنني على الرغم من كوني في الرابعة والتسعين من عمري إلا أنني أعمل إلى الآن.
And anybody who asks me, "Are you still doing this or that?"
وعندما يسألني أي شخص "ألا زلت تعملين هذا أو ذاك؟"
I don't answer because I'm not doing things still, I'm doing it like I always did.
لا أجاوبهم، لأنني لست "لا زلت" أعمل، بل أنني أعمل كما عملت دائماً
I still have -- or did I use the word still? I didn't mean that.
ولا زلت أعمل... هل استخدمت كلمة لا زلت؟ لم أقصد ذلك..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I have my file which is called To Do. I have my plans.
لدي ملف تحت اسم أشياء للعمل. لدي خططي
I have my clients. I am doing my work like I always did.
لدي زبائني. إنني أقوم بعملي كما قمت به دائماً
So this takes care of my age.
وهذا ما ينقضي عمري به
I want to show you my work so you know what I am doing and why I am here.
أريد أن أريكم عملي لكي تعرفوا ماذا أفعل ولماذا أنا هنا
This was about 1925.
هذا كان في عام ١٩٢٥ تقريباً
All of these things were made during the last 75 years.
كل هذه الأشياء قد صنعت خلال الخمسة وسبعين سنة الماضية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But, of course, I'm working since 25,
ذلك بالطبع لأنني أعمل منذ كنت في الخامسة والعشرين
doing more or less what you see here. This is Castleton China.
أقوم بما ترونه هنا. هذه صينية كاسيلتون
This was an exhibition at the Museum of Modern Art.
هذا كان معرض في متحف الفن العصري.
This is now for sale at the Metropolitan Museum.
هذه للبيع الآن في متحف الميتروبوليتان
This is still at the Metropolitan Museum now for sale.
هذه لا زالت للبيع الآن في متحف الميتروبوليتان
This is a portrait of my daughter and myself.
هذه تصوير رمزي لي مع ابنتي
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
These were just some of the things I've made.
هذه كانت فقط بعض الأشياء التي صنعتها
I made hundreds of them for the last 75 years.
صنعت المئات منها في الخمسة وسبعين سنة الماضية
I call myself a maker of things.
أسمي نفسي صانعة أشياء
I don't call myself an industrial designer because I'm other things.
لا أسمي نفسي مصممة سلع لأن هذه لست أنا
Industrial designers want to make novel things.
مصممو السلع يسعون لتصميم أشياء حديثة
Novelty is a concept of commerce, not an aesthetic concept.
الحداثة مبدأ تجاري، وليس بمبدأ جمالية
The industrial design magazine, I believe, is called "Innovation."
مجلة التصميم التجاري بحسب ظني تدعى "إنوفيشن" بمعنى الابتكار
Innovation is not part of the aim of my work.
الابتكار ليس ما أهدف إليه في عملي
Well, makers of things: they make things more beautiful, more elegant,
بالمقابل، صانعو الأشياء، يصنعون الأشياء بجمالية أكثر، بأناقة أكثر
more comfortable than just the craftsmen do.
براحة أكثر مما يفعل الحرفيون
I have so much to say. I have to think what I am going to say.
لدي الكثير لأقوله. يجب علي التفكير بما سأقوله
Well, to describe our profession otherwise,
لأصف مهنتنا بطريقة أخرى
we are actually concerned with the playful search for beauty.
نحن نهتم بالبحث المرح عن الجمال
That means the playful search for beauty was called the first activity of Man.
ذلك يعني أن البحث المرح عن الجمال كان يدعى أول نشاط للإنسان
Sarah Smith, who was a mathematics professor at MIT, wrote,
ساره سميث، والتي كانت بروفيسورة رياضيات في الإم آي تي كتبت
"The playful search for beauty was Man's first activity --
"البحث المرح عن الجمال كان أول نشاط للإنسان..
that all useful qualities and all material qualities
وكل الميزات المفيدة والميزات المادية
were developed from the playful search for beauty."
تطورت من البحث المرح عن الجمال."
These are tiles. The word, "playful" is a necessary aspect of our work
هذا كله فخار. الكلمة "مرح" لها جانب أساسي في مهنتنا
because, actually, one of our problems is that we have to make,
لأنه في الواقع إحدى مشاكلنا هي أنه يجب علينا صنع
produce, lovely things throughout all of life, and this for me is now 75 years.
وإنتاج أشياء جميلة خلال كل ما نمر به في الحياة، وذلك بالنسبة لي خمسة وسبعين عاماً الآن.
So how can you, without drying up,
فكيف لك، بدون أن تنضب،
make things with the same pleasure, as a gift to others, for so long?
أن تصنع الأشياء بنفس المتعة، كهدية للآخرين، خلال كل هذا الوقت الطويل؟
The playful is therefore an important part of our quality as designer.
لهذا السبب، المرح يلعب دوراً مهماً في طبيعتنا كمصممين
Let me tell you some about my life.
دعوني أخبركم شيئاً عن حياتي
As I said, I started to do these things 75 years ago.
كما ذكرت سابقاً، بدأت صنع هذه الأشياء منذ خمسة وسبعين سنة مضت
My first exhibition in the United States
أول معرض لي في الولايات المتحدة
was at the Sesquicentennial exhibition in 1926 --
كان في معرض سيسكويسنتينيال عام ١٩٢٦..
that the Hungarian government sent one of my hand-drawn pieces as part of the exhibit.
حيث أن الحكومة الهنقارية أرسلت إحدى أعمالي المرسومة يدوياً كجزء من المعرض
My work actually took me through many countries,
أخذني عملي إلى العديد من البلدان
and showed me a great part of the world.
وأراني جانباً عظيماً من العالم
This is not that they took me -- the work didn't take me --
ذلك ليس أن العمل أخذني إلى هناك
I made the things particularly because I wanted to use them to see the world.
بل لأنني صنعت الأشياء خصيصاً لأنني أردت أن أستخدمها لأرى العالم
I was incredibly curious to see the world, and I made all these things,
كان لدي فضول شديد لأرى العالم، وصنعت كل هذه الأشياء
which then finally did take me to see many countries and many cultures.
والتي بالأخير أخذتني العديد من الدول والثقافات
I started as an apprentice to a Hungarian craftsman,
بدأت كتلميذة لدى حرفي هنقاري
and this taught me what the guild system was in Middle Ages.
وهذا علمني كيف كان نظام النقابة في العصور الوسطى
The guild system: that means when I was an apprentice,
ما أعنيه بنظام النقابة، هو أنه عندما كنت تلميذة
I had to apprentice myself in order to become a pottery master.
كان يجب علي أن أتمرن من نفسي لأصبح خبيرة في صناعة الفخار
In my shop where I studied, or learned, there was a traditional hierarchy
في المحل حيث درست أو تعلمت، كان هناك رتب وظيفية
of master, journeyman and learned worker, and apprentice,
تتألف من الخبير، والبارع، والعامل المدرب، والتلميذ
and I worked as the apprentice.
وأنا عملت كتلميذة
The work as an apprentice was very primitive.
كان العمل كتلميذ بدائي جداً
That means I had to actually learn every aspect of making pottery by hand.
أعني أنه في الواقع كان علي تعلم كل جانب من جوانب الصناعة اليدوية للفخار
We mashed the clay with our feet when it came from the hillside.
كنا نهرس الطين المجلوب من التل بأرجلنا
After that, it had to be kneaded. It had to then go in, kind of, a mangle.
بعدها كان يجب علينا عجنه. من ثم كان يدخل في عملية أشبه بإعادة الصياغة
And then finally it was prepared for the throwing.
وأخيراً يصبح جاهزاً للرمي
And there I really worked as an apprentice.
قد كنت فعلاً أعمل كتلميذة
My master took me to set ovens
علمني الخبير إعداد الأفران
because this was part of oven-making, oven-setting, in the time.
لأن هذا العمل كان جزء من صناعة وإعداد الأفران حينذاك
And finally, I had received a document
وفي النهاية حصلت على وثيقة
that I had accomplished my apprenticeship successfully,
تنص بأنني أنجزت عملي كتلميذة بنجاح
that I had behaved morally, and this document was given to me
وبأنني تعاملت بأخلاق، وهذه الوثيقة كانت
by the Guild of Roof-Coverers, Rail-Diggers, Oven-Setters,
من نقابة صانعو الأسطح، وحفارو السكك الحديدية، ومعدو الأفران
Chimney Sweeps and Potters.
ومنظفو المداخن، وفنيو الفخار
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I also got at the time a workbook which explained my rights
حصلت كذلك في ذلك الوقت على كتاب التعليمات الذي يشرح حقوقي
and my working conditions, and I still have that workbook.
وشروط عملي، ولا زال الكتاب بحوزتي
First I set up a shop in my own garden,
في البداية أسست محلاً في حديقتي الخاصة
and made pottery which I sold on the marketplace in Budapest.
وصنعت فخارات للبيع في ساحة البيع في بودابست
And there I was sitting, and my then-boyfriend --
وهناك كنت أجلس مع صديقي وقتها
I didn't mean it was a boyfriend like it is meant today --
ولا أعني بكلمة صديقي ما تعنيه في هذه الأيام..
but my boyfriend and I sat at the market and sold the pots.
كنا نجلس أنا وصديقي في السوق ونبيع الجرات
My mother thought that this was not very proper,
أمي لم تر بأن ذلك كان لائقاً
so she sat with us to add propriety to this activity.
لذا فقد كانت تجلس معنا لتضيف الانضباط لهذا التصرف
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
However, after a while there was a new factory being built in Budapest,
مع ذلك، بعد فترة كان هناك مصنع جديد يبنى في بودابست
a pottery factory, a large one.
كان مصنع فخار، وكان ضخماً
And I visited it with several ladies, and asked all sorts of questions of the director.
وقد زرته مع عدة نساء، ووجهت كل أنواع الأسئلة للمدير
Then the director asked me, why do you ask all these questions?
عندها سألني المدير، لماذا تطرحين كل هذه الأسئلة؟
I said, I also have a pottery.
أجبته بأنني أنا كذلك أملك محلاً للفخار
So he asked me, could he please visit me, and then finally he did,
فسألني إذا كان بإمكانه زيارتي، ثم أخيراً زارني
and explained to me that what I did now in my shop was an anachronism,
وشرح لي بأن ما أفعله الآن في محلي يعتبر قديم الطراز
that the industrial revolution had broken out,
وبأن الثورة الصناعية قد بدأت
and that I rather should join the factory.
وأنه من الأفضل لي أن أنضم إلى المصنع
There he made an art department for me where I worked for several months.
وهناك في المصنع أنشأ لي قسم للفن حيث عملت لعدة أشهر
However, everybody in the factory spent his time at the art department.
ولكن كان كل الذين في المصنع يقضون وقتهم في قسم الفن
The director there said there were several women casting
عندها قال المدير بأن هناك عدة نساء
and producing my designs now in molds, and this was sold also to America.
يوزعون ويصنعون تصاميمي في قوالب، وأنها تباع حتى في أمريكا
I remember that it was quite successful.
أتذكر بأنها لاقت نجاحاً كبيراً
However, the director, the chemist, model maker -- everybody --
على الرغم من ذلك، كل من المدير، وعالم الكيمياء، وصانع القوالب.. الكل..
concerned himself much more with the art department --
اهتموا أكثر بقسم الفن..
that means, with my work -- than making toilets,
مما يعني بأنهم اهتموا بفني، أكثر من صناعة المراحيض
so finally they got a letter from the center, from the bank who owned the factory,
لذا أخيراً تلقوا رسالة من المركز، من المصرف الذي يملك المصنع
saying, make toilet-setting behind the art department, and that was my end.
تأمر بإنشاء مصنع مراحيض خلف قسم الفن، وهذه كانت نهايتي
So this gave me the possibility because now I was a journeyman,
لذا، هذا أعطاني الفرصة لأنني بعدها أصبحت بارعة
and journeymen also take their satchel and go to see the world.
والبارعون أيضاً يستطيعون شد رحالهم ليذهبوا ويروا العالم
So as a journeyman, I put an ad into the paper that I had studied,
لذا، كبارعة، وضعت إعلاناً في الجريدة ينص على أنني درست
that I was a down-to-earth potter's journeyman
وعلى أنني صانعة فخار متواضعة بارعة
and I was looking for a job as a journeyman.
وأبحث عن فرصة عمل كبارعة في صناعة الفخار
And I got several answers, and I accepted the one
وحصلت على العديد من الأجوبة، ووافقت على
which was farthest from home and practically, I thought, halfway to America.
العرض الذي كان سيأخذني أبعد من المنزل، وخصيصاً كما حسبت، أقرب إلى أمريكا
And that was in Hamburg.
وذلك كان في هامبورغ
Then I first took this job in Hamburg, at an art pottery
بعدها أخذت أولاً هذه الوظيفة في هامبورغ، في مشغل فني للفخار
where everything was done on the wheel,
حيث كان كل شيء مصنوع على العجلة
and so I worked in a shop where there were several potters.
لذا اشتغلت في المحل مع العديد من صانعي الفخار
And the first day, I was coming to take my place at the turntable --
وفي أول يوم، قدمت لآخذ مكاني عند القرص الدائري..
there were three or four turntables -- and one of them, behind where I was sitting,
كان هناك ثلاث أو أربع أقراص دائرية.. وخلف إحداهم حيث كنت أجلس
was a hunchback, a deaf-mute hunchback, who smelled very bad.
كان هناك أحدب، كان أصم وأخرس كذلك، وذات رائحة نتنة
So I doused him in cologne every day, which he thought was very nice,
لذا كنت أغمره بالكولونيا كل يوم، وقد كان يجده بالأمر الطيب جداً
and therefore he brought bread and butter every day,
لذا كان يجلب لي الخبز والزبدة كل يوم
which I had to eat out of courtesy.
وكنت أضطر إلى الأكل من باب المجاملة
The first day I came to work in this shop
أول يوم قدمت فيه إلى العمل في المحل
there was on my wheel a surprise for me.
كانت هناك مفاجأة بانتظاري على عجلتي
My colleagues had thoughtfully put on the wheel where I was supposed to work
زملائي في العمل وضعوها بطيبة على العجلة حيث يفترض أن أعمل
a very nicely modeled natural man's organs.
كانت عبارة عن منحوتة دقيقة لعضو ذكري
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
After I brushed them off with a hand motion, they were very --
بعد أن دفعتها بيدي مزيحةً إياها، كانوا شديدي الـ--
I finally was now accepted, and worked there for some six months.
أخيراً كنت قد انقبلت، وعملت هناك لستة أشهر تقريباً
This was my first job.
هذه كانت أول وظيفة لي
If I go on like this, you will be here till midnight.
إذا استمريت على هذا المنوال ستجدون أنفسكم هنا حتى منتصف الليل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So I will try speed it up a little
لذا سأحاول الإسراع في الحديث قليلاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Moderator: Eva, we have about five minutes.
إيفا، ما زال لدينا حوالي خمسة دقائق
Eva Zeisel: Are you sure?
هل أنت متأكد؟
Moderator: Yes, I am sure.
نعم أنا كذلك
EZ: Well, if you are sure,
حسناً، إذا كنت متأكداً
I have to tell you that within five minutes I will talk very fast.
فعلي أن أتحدث بسرعة شديدة خلال هذه الخمسة دقائق
And actually, my work took me to many countries
وفعلاً أخذني عملي لعدة بلدان
because I used my work to fill my curiosity.
لأنني استخدمته لأشبع فضولي
And among other things, other countries I worked, was in the Soviet Union,
ومن بين الأشياء الأخرى، البلدان الأخرى التي عملت فيها، كان الاتحاد السوفييتي
where I worked from '32 to '37 -- actually, to '36.
حيث عملت من ١٩٣٢ إلى ١٩٣٧.. في الواقع إلى ١٩٧٦
I was finally there, although I had nothing to do -- I was a foreign expert.
كنت أخيراً قد وصلت إلى تلك النقطة، على الرغم من عدم حصولي على شيء أعمله، كنت خبيرة أجنبية
I became art director of the china and glass industry,
أصبحت مخرجة فنية للصناعة الصينية والزجاج
and eventually under Stalin's purges -- at the beginning of Stalin's purges,
وفي الأخير تحت التطهير الستاليني، في بداية التطهير الستاليني
I didn't know that hundreds of thousands of innocent people were arrested.
لم أكن أعلم بأن مئات الآلاف من الأبرياء كانو يُعتقلون
So I was arrested quite early in Stalin's purges,
لذا أنا اعتقلت في بداية التطهير الستاليني
and spent 16 months in a Russian prison.
وقضيت ١٦ شهراً في السجن الروسي
The accusation was that I had successfully prepared an Attentat on Stalin's life.
كانت التهمة بأنني نجحت في إعداد مهزلة بحياة ستالين
This was a very dangerous accusation.
كانت تهمة خطيرة
And if this is the end of my five minutes, I want to tell you that
وإذا كانت هذه هي نهاية الخمس دقائق، فأريد أن أخبركم
I actually did survive, which was a surprise.
بأنني عشت بالفعل، بشكل مفاجئ
But since I survived and I'm here,
لكن بما أنني عشت وبما أنني هنا
and since this is the end of the five minutes, I will --
وبما أنها نهاية الخمس دقائق، فإنني سـ...
Moderator: Tell me when your last trip to Russia was.
أخبريني عن متى كانت رحلتك الأخيرة لروسيا
Weren't you there recently?
ألم تكوني هناك من مدة قريبة؟
EZ: Oh, this summer, in fact,
أوه، هذا الصيف في الواقع
the Lomonosov factory was bought by an American company, invited me.
دعتني الشركة الأمريكية التي اشترت مصنع اللومونوسوف
They found out that I had worked in '33 at this factory,
عرفوا بأنني اشتغلت في ذاك المصنع في ١٩٣٣
and they came to my studio in Rockland County,
وحضروا إلى مشغلي في دولة روكلاند
and brought the 15 of their artists to visit me here.
وأحضروا معهم ١٥ من فنانيهم ليزوروني هنا
And they invited myself to come to the Russian factory last summer,
كما دعوني لأحضر إلى المصنع الروسي الصيف الفائت
in July, to make some dishes, design some dishes.
في يوليو، لأصنع بعض الأواني، أو لأصمم بعض الأواني
And since I don't like to travel alone, they also invited my daughter,
وبما أنني لا أحب السفر لوحدي، دعوا معي ابنتي
son-in-law and granddaughter,
وصهري وحفيدتي
so we had a lovely trip to see Russia today,
وقد كانت رحلة جميلة رأينا فيها روسيا هذه الأيام
which is not a very pleasant and happy view.
والتي لم تكن بالمنظر الذي يبهج النفس
Here I am now, if this is the end? Thank you.
ها أنا ذا الآن، إذا كانت هذه نهاية الحديث. شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)